Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）、Savior Michael
压制&&特效：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
校对：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
特别感谢：裘宗燕教授
Henderson-Escher的例子
Henderson-Escher Example
上节课我们讨论了复合数据
PROFESSOR: Well, last time we talked about compound data,
其中有两个关键点
and there were two main points to that business.
首先 有一种数据抽象的方法学
First of all, there was a methodology of data abstraction,
其要点是将数据的使用
and the point of that was that you could isolate the way that data objects are used
和表示分离开来
from the way that they're represented:
比如说 我们可以与一个叫做George的人“签订契约”
this idea that there's this guy, George, and you go out make a contract with him;
让他负责数据的表示
and it's his business to represent the data objects;
而当我们使用这些数据的时候
and at the moment you are using them,
不需要替George操心他是如何完成数据表示的工作的
you don't think about George's problem.
其次 Lisp中有一种特殊的方式把对象连接在一起
And then secondly, there was this particular way that Lisp has of gluing together things
就是构成“序对”
to form objects called pairs,
这是通过CONS CAR CDR实现的
and that's done with cons, car and cdr.
而CONS CAR CDR本身是如何实现的 这不重要
And the way that cons, car and cdr are implemented is basically irrelevant.
George的任务就是如何构建这些东西
That's sort of George's problem of how to build those things.
可以将它们实现为基本过程
It could be done as primitives.
也可以利用一些奇怪的过程来实现
It could be done using procedures in some weird way,
但是我们不用操心这些
but we're not going to worry about that.
举个例子 我们来看下有理数算术
And as an example, we looked at rational number arithmetic.
看下向量
We looked at vectors,
我们简单回顾一下向量
and here's just a review of vectors.
这里有个对两个向量求和的操作
Here's an operation that takes the sum of of two vectors,
我们想要把向量v1和v2相加
so we want to add this vector, v1, and this vector, v2, and we get the sum.
它们的和也是一个向量 其坐标是两个向量的坐标的和
And the sum is the vector whose coordinates are the sum of the coordinates of the pieces you're adding.
所以 定义(+VECT V1 V2)为
So I can say, to define make-vect, right, to add two vectors
我创建一个向量 其X坐标是两向量X坐标的和
I make a vector, whose x coordinate is the sum of the two x coordinates,
而Y坐标是两向量Y坐标的和
and whose y coordinate is the sum of the two y coordinates.
类似地 我们也可以定义一个缩放向量的操作
And then similarly, we could have an operation that scales vectors,
这里的SCALE过程是用数字S乘以向量V
so here's a procedure scale that multiplies a vector, v, by some number, s.
向量V从这里到这里
So here's v, v goes from there to there
我放大V 得到了与原来同向但更长的向量
and I scale v, and I get a vector in the same direction that's longer.
为了缩放向量 我需要通过缩放坐标来实现
And again, to scale a vector, I multiply the successive coordinates.
所以我构建了一个向量 它的X坐标是原向量X坐标的S倍
So I make a vector, whose x coordinate is the scale factor times the x coordinate
同时 它的Y坐标是原来向量Y坐标的S倍
and whose y coordinate is the scale factor times the y coordinate.
上述两个操作都是利用了向量的表示来实现的
So those are two operations that are implemented using the representation of vectors.
而这种向量的表示 我们则可以用序对来实现
And the representation of vectors, for instance, is something that we can build in terms of pairs.
因此George需要为我们提供MAKE-VECTOR、XCOR和YCOR
So George has gone out and implemented for us make-vector and x coordinate and y coordinate,
他可以使用CONS CAR CDR来实现
and this could be done, for instance, using cons,car and cdr;
但是注意 我这里用了一个略微不同的方式
and notice here, I wrote this in a slightly different way.
这个过程我们之前看过 其中我讲过
The procedures we've seen before, I've said something like
(MAKE-VECTOR X Y)也就是(CONS X Y)
say, make-vector of x and y: cons of x and y.
而我这里简单定义MAKE-VECTOR为CONS
And here I just wrote make-vector cons.
这就与之前有些不同了
And that means something slightly different.
之前我们我们把MAKE-VECTOR定义为需要两个参数的过程
Previously we'd say, define make-vector to be a procedure that takes two arguments, x and y,
效果是(CONS X Y)
and does cons of x and y.
这里 我就把MAKE-VECTOR定义为CONS
And here I am saying define make-vector to be the thing that cons is,
这跟我们之前使用的方式基本上是一样的
and that's almost the same as the other way we've been writing things.
大家要习惯于“过程也是对象 而且你可以给他们命名”这种想法
And I just want you to get used to the idea that procedures can be objects, and that you can name them.
这些就是向量的表示方法了
OK, well there's vector representation, and again,
如果仅仅是那样 那就太无趣了
if that was all there was to it,this would all be pretty boring.
要记住 要点是我们不仅可以通过使用CONS将数字组合成序对
And the point is, remember, that you can use cons to glue together not just numbers to form pairs,
也可以组合任何东西
but to glue together arbitrary things.
例如 如果我想表示一个线段
So for instance, if we'd like to represent a line segment,
一个以某个向量为起点的线段
say the line segment that goes from a certain vector:
比如从向量(2,3)所代表的起点到向量(5,1)所代表的终点的线段
say, the segment from the vector 2,3 to the point represented by the vector 5,1.
如果我们想表示这条线段
If we want to represent that line segment,
那么我们可以构建一个序对的序对
then we can build that as a pair of pairs.
这样我们就可以表示一条线段了
So again, we can represent line segments.
我们可以编写一个使用CONS构造线段的构造函数
We can make a constructor that makes a segment using cons,
以及 析取出线段起点、终点的选择函数
selects out the start of a segment, selects out the end point of the segment;
那么如果我们剥开抽象层一探究竟
and then if we actually look at that, if we peel away the abstraction layers,
就会发现线段不过是 序对组成的序对
and see what's that really is a pair of pairs,
它还是一个序对
we'd say well that's a pair.
这里有个线段
Here's the segment.
它的CAR部分是个序对 CDR部分也是个序对
It's car, right, it's car pointer is a pair, and it's cdr is also a pair,
它的CAR部分是由2和3构成的序对
and then what the car is--here's the car, that itself is a pair of 2 and 3.
CDR部分则由5和1构成的序对
And similarly the cdr is a pair of 2 and 3.
这里我再提醒大家一下
And let me remind you again
好多人认为如果我箭头向下画的话
that a lot of people have some idea that if I'd taken this arrow and somehow
会有其它的含意
written it to point down, that would mean something else.
这是不对的
That's irrelevant.
箭头指示的是对象间如何连接 它指向水平或竖直方向都是无关紧要的
It's only how these are connected and not whether this arrow happens to go vertically or horizontally.
还要提醒一下 序对是具有闭包性质的
And again just to remind you, there was this notion of closure.
闭包性质使我们可以构建更复杂的东西 而不仅仅是简单的序对
See, closure was the thing that allowed us to start building up complexity, that didn't trap us in pairs.
在这里我要特别指出 在我们用CONS构建出来的序对的基础上
Particularly what I mean is the things that we make, having combined things using cons to get a pair,
我们也可以进一步用CONS来构造更复杂的对象
those things themselves can be combined using cons to make more complicated things.
或者用数学家的话说 Lisp中的数据对象在CONS运算下是封闭的
Or as a mathematician might say, the set of data objects in Lisp is closed under the operation of forming pairs.
这个性质使我们能够构造更加复杂的数据对象
That's the thing that allows us to build complexity.
这个似乎是显然的 但是要记住
And that seems obvious, but remember
人们使用的编程语言中有很多东西并不是封闭的
a lot of the things in the computer languages that people use are not closed.
举例来说 Basic和Fortran中的构造数组操作 就不是封闭的
So for example, forming arrays in Basic and Fortran is not a closed operation,
因为 虽然你可以用数字、字符或字符串等来构造数组
because you can make an array of numbers or character strings or something,
但是你不能创建数组的数组
but you can't make an array of arrays.
当考察某种组合的方法时
And when you look at means of combination
你应该考察该组合方法是否封闭
you should be asking yourself whether things are closed under that means of combination.
不管怎样 因为我们可以构造序对的序对
Well in any case, because we can form pairs of pairs,
我们就可以用序对将数据以各种各样的方式组合起来
we can start using pairs to glue things together in all sorts of different ways.
比如我想要组合四个数 —— 1 2 3 4
So for instance if I'd like to glue together the four things, 1, 2, 3 and 4,
我有很多方法
there are a lot of ways I can do it.
比如 像构造线段那样 我可以构造一个序对
I could, for example, like we did with that line segment, i could make a pair
它是((1 2) (3 4)) 对吧？
that had a 1 and a 2 and a 3 and a 4, right?
或者如果我喜欢 我可以像这样做
Or if I liked, I could do something like this.
我构造一个序对 它的CAR部分也是一个序对
I could make a pair, whose first thing is a pair,
这个序对的CAR部分为1 而CDR部分为由2、3构成的序对
whose car is 1, and his cdr is itself a pair that has the 2 and the 3
最后 我把4放在这里
and then I could put the 4 up here.
所以你可以看到 组合对象的方式有很多种
So you see, there are a lot of different ways that I can start using pairs to glue things together,
因此就有必要建立一些统一的约定
and so it'll be a good idea to establish some kind of conventions,right,
使我们能够用某种的通用的方式处理数据
that allow us to deal with this thing in some conventional way,
而不用总是针对具体问题做一些生硬的选择
so we're not constantly making an ad hoc choice.
Lisp里面就有这样一种约定
And Lisp has a particular convention
这个约定将一系列的东西表示成一个序对组成的链
for representing a sequence of things as, essentially, a chain of pairs,
而这样一个数据序列就叫做一个“表”
and that's called a List.
表本质上就是Lisp用来表示序列数据的一个约定而已
And what a list is is essentially just a convention for representing a sequence.
我可以使用序对的序列来表示序列 1 2 3 4
I would represent the sequence 1, 2, 3 and 4 by a sequence of pairs.
我把1放在这里 它的CDR指向另一个序对
I'd put 1 here and then the cdr of this would point to another pair
这个序对的CAR部分是序列中的下一个数
whose car was the next thing in the sequence,
并且它的CDR指向了另一个序对
and the cdr would point to another pair
它的CAR部分是序列的再下一个数
whose car was the next thing in the sequence--
这个是3
so there's 3--
以此类推
and then another one.
所以 序列中的每一个元素都对应着一个序对
So for each item in the sequence, I'll get a pair.
而当这个序列中没有其它元素时，我用一个特殊的标记
And now there are no more, so I put a special marker
来表示列表中没有元素了
that means there's nothing more in the List.
好 这就是将序列中的元素组合起来的一种约定方式
OK, so that's a conventional way to glue things together if you want to represent a sequence, right.
而它其实就是一堆序对
And what it is is a bunch of pairs,
每个序对中的CAR部分就是我们想要组合到一起的元素
the successive cars of each pair are the items that you want to glue together,
这些序对的CDR部分则指向下一个序对
and the cdr pointer points to the next pair.
现在 如果我想要构造它 我需要向Lisp中输入
Now if I actually wanted to construct that, what I would type into Lisp is this:
我会像这样来构造
I'd actually construct that as saying, well this thing is
(CONS 1 (CONS 2 (CONS 3 (CONS 4 NIL))))
the cons of 1 onto the cons of 2 onto the cons of 3 onto
the cons of 4 onto, well, this thing nil.
NIL是序列末尾标志的名字
And what nil is is a name for the end of List marker.
它是一个特殊的名字 标识以达到表的末尾
It's a special name, which means this is the end of the List.
好 这就是如何构造一个表
OK, so that's how I would actually construct that.
如果每次构造一个表时 都要输入像
Of course, it's a terrible drag to constantly have to write something like
(CONS 1 (CONS 2 (CONS 3...的话 将会非常费力
the cons of 1 onto the cons of 2 onto the cons of 3, whenever you want to make this thing.
因此Lisp提供了一种叫做LIST的操作
So Lisp has an operation that's called LIST,
LIST其实是这种嵌套CONS的缩写
and List is just an abbreviation for this nest of conses.
它可以让我用(LIST 1 2 3 4)来构造表
So I could say, I could construct that by saying that is the List of 1, 2, 3 and 4.
这只是另外一种方式v一个语法糖
And all this is is another way, a piece of syntactic sugar,
用来简便地书写嵌套的CONS
a more convenient way for writing that chain of conses--
(CONS (CONS (CONS (CONS NIL))))
cons of cons of cons of cons of cons of cons onto nil.
举例来说 我将构造一个表(1 2 3 4) 并把它叫做1-TO-4
So for example, I could build this thing and say, I'll define 1-TO-4 to be the List of 1, 2, 3 and 4.
注意使用这种简便写法的结果
OK, well notice some of the consequences of using this convention.
首先 如果我有这个表(1 2 3 4)
First of all if I have this List, this 1, 2, 3 and 4,
表的CAR把部分就是这个表的第一个元素 对吧？
the car of the whole thing is the first element in the List, right.
那么 如何获得元素2呢？
How do I get 2?
2应该是1-TO-4的CDR部分的CAR部分
Well, 2 would be the car of the cdr of this thing 1-TO-4, it would be 2, right.
它的CDR是这个
I take this thing, I take the cdr of it, which is this much,
而它的CAR部分是2
and the car of that is 2,
同理 1-TO-4的CDR的CDR的CAR部分
and then similarly, the car of the cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4, cdr, cdr, car--
是3 以此类推
would give me 3, and so on.
我们来看下屏幕
Let's take a look at that on the computer screen for a second.
我定义一个表(1 2 3 4) 命名为1-TO-4
I could come up to List, and I could type define 1-TO-4 to be the List of 1, 2, 3 and 4, right.
我这样写 计算机返回定义完成 这个就是1-TO-4的定义
And I'll tell that to Lisp, and it says, fine, that's the definition of 1-TO-4.
我问 比如 1-TO-4的CDR的CDR的CAR
And I could say, for instance, what's the car of the cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4, close paren, close paren.
嗯 它是3
Right, so the car of the cdr of the cdr would be 3.
或者我问 1-TO-4是什么
Right, or I could say, what's 1-TO-4 itself.
Lisp输出的是用括号包围的 (1 2 3 4)
And you see what Lisp typed out is 1, 2, 3, 4, enclosed in parentheses,
用括号将表中的元素包围起来的这种记号
and this notation, typing the elements of the List enclosed in parentheses
通常用来打印输出表示序列的序对链
is Lisp's conventional way for printing back this chain of pairs that represents a sequence.
又比如 我问1-TO-4的CDR部分是什么
So for example, if I said, what's the cdr of 1-TO-4,
结果是表的剩余部分
that's going to be the rest of the List.
这是原表首元素所指向的序对 新序列从2开始
That's the thing pointed to by the first pair, which is, again, a sequence that starts off with 2.
比如 1-TO-4的CDR的CDR部分是什么
Or for example, I go off and say, what's the cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4;
返回(3 4)
then that's 3,4.
或者 1-TO-4的CDR的CDR的CDR的CDR部分是什么
Or if I say, what's the cdr of the cdr of the cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4,
我们看一下表的尾指针 Lisp返回()
and I'm down there looking at the end of List pointer itself, and Lisp prints that as just open paren, close paren.
你们可以认为这是一个空表
You can think of that as a List with nothing in there.
我求取 1-TO-4的CDR的CDR的CDR部分
All right, see at the end what I did there was I looked at the cdr of the cdr of the cdr of 1-TO-4,
这就只剩下表尾指针本身
and I'm just left with the end of List pointer itself.
它的输出是()
And that gets printed as open close.
好了 这是处理表的一种常见方式
All right, well that's a conventional way you can see for working down a List
也就是不断地取CDR部分
by taking successive cdrs of things.
这个叫做表的CDRING
It's called cdring down a List.
当然手写这些CDR非常费劲
And of course it's pretty much of a drag to type all those cdrs by hand.
我们没必要这么做 我们编写程序来这么做
You don't do that. You write procedures that do that.
事实上 Lisp中非常普遍的事情是写一些过程
And in fact one very, very common thing to do in Lisp is to write procedures that,
表中所有元素进行某种操作 得到的是由结果构成的表
sort of, take a List of things and do something to every element in List, and return you a List of the results.
比如 我写一个SCALE-LIST的过程
So what I mean for example, is I might write a procedure called Scale-List,
我要用SCALE-LIST将表1-TO-4放大10倍
and Scale-List I might say I want to scale by 10 the entire List 1-TO-4,
那么它应该返回表(10 20 30 40)
and that would return for me the List 10, 20, 30, 40.
没错 它返回一个表
Right, it returns List, and
我们可以猜想到这当中采用了某种递归策略
well you can see that there's going to be some kind of recursive strategy for doing it.
我应该如何编写这个过程呢？
How would I actually write that procedure?
如果要构建一个每个元素都乘以10的列表
The idea would be, well if you'd like to build up a List where you've multiplied every element by 10,
需要做的是—假设已经得到了结果表的剩余元素
what you'd say is well you imagine that you'd taken the rest of the List--
也就是表的CDR部分
right, the thing represented by the cdr of the List,
这个子表中的每个元素都是原来元素乘以10
and suppose I'd already built a List where each of these was multiplied by 10--
这是SCALE-LIST对表CDR部分作用的结果
that would be Scale-List of the cdr of the List.
我需要做的 就只有用表的CAR部分乘以10
And then all I have to do is multiply the car of the List by 10,
然后用CONS将它和剩余部分连接起来 并返回这个列表
and then cons that onto the rest, and I'll get a List.
类似地 为了缩放子表 我得先缩放子表的CDR部分
Right and then similarly, to have scaled the cdr of the List, I'll scale the cdr of that
并将其与2*10连接起来
cons onto that 2 multiplied by 10.
最终 当我处理到表尾时 这里就只剩表尾指针了
And finally when I get all the way down to the end, and I only have this end of List pointer.
它叫做NIL 我就直接返回表尾指针
All right, this thing whose name is nil-- well I just returned an end of List pointer.
所以这就是这个过程的递归策略
So there's a recursive strategy for doing that.
这个过程就是这样
Here's the actual procedure that does that.
这个例子就是对表做CDRING操作的通用策略
Right, this is an example of the general strategy of cdr-ing down a List and
也就是所谓的“通过CONS组合结果”
so called cons-ing up the result, right.
那么 对表L缩放S倍 我该如何做呢？
So to Scale a List l by some scale factor s, what do I do?
首先得做判断 Lisp中有个叫NULL?的谓词
Well there's a test, and Lisp has the predicate called null.
NULL?判断对象是否为表尾
Null means is this thing the end of List pointer,
或者说 对象是否为空表
or another way to think of that is are there any elements in this List, right.
任何情况下 当我处理到表尾时 我就将其返回
But in any case if I'm looking at the end of List pointer, then I just return the end of List pointer.
简单地返回NIL
I just return nil,
否则 我就用CONS把列表中的第一个元素经过操作（缩放）后的结果
otherwise I cons together the result of doing what I'm going to do to the first element in the List,
就是说 取L的CAR部分 然后用它乘以S
namely taking the car of l and multiplying it by s,
然后我就用CONS将这个结果 与用递归形式缩放后的表的剩下部分 连接在一起
and I cons that onto recursively scaling the rest of the List.
再说一次 总体的思想是
OK, so again, the general idea is that you
你要用递归的方式处理表中的剩余元素 即表的CDR部分
you recursively do something to the rest of the List, to the cdr of the List,
然后你用CONS将那部分的结果 与经过处理后的表的第一个元素连接在一起
and then you cons that onto actually doing something to the first element of the List.
当你处理到结尾的时候 返回表尾标志NIL
When you get down to the end here, you return the end of List pointer,
这就是对一个表里的数据做某种操作的通用模式
and that's a general pattern for doing something to a list.
现在 你们应该清楚知道这样一个事实
Well of course you should know by now that the very fact
也就是我不必额外为这种基本模式额外编写过程
that there's a general pattern there means I shouldn't be writing this procedure at all.
我要做的事情就是写一个过程
What I should do is write a procedure
这是这个基本模式
that's the general pattern itself
对表中的元素执行操作 并以表的形式返回结果
that says, do something to everything in the List and define this thing in terms of that.
好了 我们定义一些高阶过程
Right, make some higher order procedure,
我们定义一个叫MAP的高阶过程 来完成这些操作
and here's the higher order procedure that does that. It's called MAP,
MAP以表L和过程P为参数
and what MAP does is it takes a List, takes a List l, and it takes a procedure p,
并返回对表L中每个元素应用过程P后得到的新表
and it returns the List of the elements gotten by applying p to each successive element in the List.
这个新表里的元素是(P E1) (P E2) ...  到(P En)
All right, so p of e1, p of e2, p of en.
所以我指的就是对一个表做这样一种变换：将P应用到表的每一个元素上
Right, so I think of taking this List and transforming it by applying p to each element.
你们看到的这些过程正是我提到的通用策略
And you see all this procedure is is exactly the general strategy I said.
我们用它写乘以10的过程
Instead of multiply by 10, it's do the procedure.
如果表是空的 则返回NIL
If the List is empty, return nil.
否则 对表的首元素应用P
Otherwise, apply p to the first element of the List.
将P应用于L的CAR部分
Right, apply p to car of l,
然后连接它和将P应用于表CDR部分中的剩余元素得到的子表连接起来
and cons that onto the result of applying p to everything in the cdr of the List,
这就是一个通用过程——MAP
so that's a general procedure called MAP.
我们可以用MAP来定义SCALE-LIST
And I could define Scale-List in terms of MAP.
我给你们展示一下
Let me show you that first.
SCALE-LIST就是对表MAP一个特定的过程
But I could say Scale-List is another way to define it is just MAP along the List by the procedure,
这个过程需要一个参数 返回给定参数乘以S的结果
which takes an item and multiplies it by s.
所以我思考缩放表这个过程的正确方式应该是
Right, so this is really the way I should think about scaling the List,
将这种递归实质实现为通用策略 而不是一个具体针对的过程
build that actual recursion into the general strategy, not to every particular procedure I write.
当然 这样做的意义之一是 是你会开始发现共性
And of course, one of the values of doing this is that you start to see commonality.
我们正在掌握使用通用模式
Right, again you're capturing general patterns of usage.
比如 (MAP SQUARE 1-TO-4) 返回(1 4 9 16)
For instance, if I said MAP, the square procedure, down this List 1-TO-4, then I'd end up with 1, 4, 9 and 16.
对这个表做映射
Right, or if I said MAP down this List,
用(LAMBDA (X) (+ X 10))映射表1-TO-4
lambda of x plus x 10, if I MAP that down 1-TO-4,
我让表的每个元素都加了10
then I'd get the List where everything had 10 added to it:
也就是得到了(11 12 13 14)
right, so I'd get 11,12, 13, 14.
我们看到对表中每个元素做操作是一种非常普遍的想法
And you can see that's going to be a very, very common idea: doing something to every element in the List.
而大家需要思考如何编写MAP的迭代版本
One thing you might think about is writing MAP in an iterative style.
我碰巧写的是一个递归版本
The one I wrote happens to evolve a recursive process,
但是我们也可以很容易地把它改成迭代过程
but we could just as easily have made one that evolves an iterative process.
有趣的是 一旦你开始用MAP来思考
But see the interesting thing about it is that once you start thinking in terms of MAP--
比如 一旦把缩放看作是一种MAP 就不用关心是迭代还是递归实现
see, once you say scale is just MAP, you stop thinking about whether it's iterative or recursive,
你只会关心 啊 这里有这样一种数据集合 有这样一个表
and you just say, well there's this aggregate, there's this List,
我要做的是转化表中的每个元素
and what I do is transform every item in the List,
而不去考虑特别的控制流程或顺序
and I stop thinking about the particular control structure in order.
这是个非常非常重要的想法
That's a very, very important idea,
我猜这个想法来自APL语言
and it, I guess it really comes out of APL.
它是APL中非常重要的思想
It's, sort of, the really important idea in APL
即不要去考虑控制结构
that you stop thinking about control structures,
而是关注于策略操作
and you start thinking about operations on aggregates,
在本课程进行到一半的时候 我们将讨论一种叫做流处理的东西
and then about halfway through this course,we'll see when we talk about something called stream processing,
那时我们将看到这种观点的真正威力
how that view of the world really comes into its glory.
这是一种很聪明的思想
This is just us a, sort of, cute idea.
我们可以在以后看到更多应用
But we'll see much more applications of that later on.
还有一些非常有用也非常像MAP的过程
Well let me mention that there's something that's very similar to MAP that's also a useful idea, and that's--
MAP是将某个过程应用于表中每个元素
see, MAP says I take a List, I apply something to each item,
并返回相应结果构成的表
and I return a List of the successive values.
还有一种与此非常非常相似的操作
There's another thing I might do, which is very, very similar,
也就是给定一个列表和操作 依次将其应用于表中每个元素
which is take a List and some action you want to do and then do it to each item in the List in sequence.
而不会建立由结果构成的表 只是为了完成操作
Don't make a List of the values, just do this particular action,
这个过程非常像MAP
and that's something that's very much like MAP.
它就是FOR-EACH
It's called for-each,
它接受一个过程和一个表
and for-each takes a procedure and a List,
它实际上是对表中每个元素执行此操作
and what it's going to do is do something to every item in the List.
通常是这样 如果表非空
So basically what it does: it says if the List is not empty,
也就是不为NIL
if the List is not null,
我将这个过程应用于表的第一个元素
then what I do is, I apply my procedure to the first item in the List,
然后对表中其余元素做同样的事情
and then I do this thing to the rest of the List.
我将FOR-EACH也应用于表的CDR部分
I apply for-each to the cdr of the List.
我对表的首元素进行处理 然后对表其余部分进行处理
All right, so I do it to the first of the List, do it to the rest of the List,
当然 以此类推 递归地调用 又会对表其余部分的其余部分做处理
and of course, when I call it recursively, that's going to do it to the rest of the rest of the List and so on.
最终 过程结束时 我应该告知系统
And finally, when I get done, I have to just do something to say I'm done,
所以就返回“DONE” 所以这非常像MAP
so we'll return the message "done." So that's very, very similar to MAP.
它们之间只是返回值不同
It's mostly different in what it returns.
比如说 如果我有一个可以在屏幕上打印对象的过程
And so for example, if I had some procedure that printed things on the screen,
如果我想打印表中的所有元素 可以调用(FOR-EACH PRINT LIST)
if I wanted to print everything in the List, I could say for-each, print this List.
如果我有一系列图表构成的表 想把它们输出在屏幕上
Or if I had a List of figures, and I wanted to draw them on the display,
我可以对这个调用(FOR-EACH DISPLAY FIGURES)
I could say for-each, display on the screen this figure.
有问题么？
Take questions.
学生：除非你明确地指定
AUDIENCE: Does it create a new copy with something done to it,
Lisp会创建一个你正在处理的对象的新拷贝 是这样么？
unless you explicitly tell it to do that? Is that correct?
教授：对
PROFESSOR: Right. Ah.
就是这样
Yeah, that's right.
FOR-EACH不创建新列表 它只是对列表的每一个元素进行处理
For-each does not create a List. It just sort of does something.
所以如果你有一堆事情等着做
So if you have a bunch of things you want to do
并且你并不关心这些值 比如打印 绘图
and you're not worried about values like printing something, or drawing something on the screen,
或者在终端中响铃等等
or ringing the bell on the terminal,or for something,
FOR-EACH对表中每个元素做这些事
you can say for-each, you know, do this for-each of those things in the List,
而MAP其实构建了一个新集合 这个集合也许是你想要用的
whereas MAP actually builds you this new collection of values that you might want to use.
这就是它们之间的微妙关系
It's just a subtle difference between them.
学生：你能否用FOR-EACH来构造MAP
AUDIENCE: Could you write MAP using for-each,
其中你用类似CONS的操作将表又构造出来了？
so that you did some sort of cons or something to build the List back up?
教授：某种程度上 我也许可以
PROFESSOR: Well, sort of. I mean, I probably could.
我不知道如何随手写出它 但是我可以给一些思路
I can't think of how to do it right offhand, but yeah, I could arrange something.
学生：根据昨天的课程 我认为MAP和FOR-EACH的关键区别在于
AUDIENCE: The vital difference between MAP and for-each is one is recursive and the other is not
它们之中一个是递归的 而另一个不是
in the sense you defined early yesterday, I believe.
教授：是的 关于MAP和FOR-EACH和递归
PROFESSOR: Yeah, about MAP and for-each and recursion.
这个观点很好
Yeah, that's a good point.
我写的MAP过程恰巧是一个递归过程
For the MAP procedure I wrote, that happens to be a recursive process.
这是因为 你需要得到处理完表的剩余部分后的值
And the reason for that is that when you've done this thing to the rest of the List,
使其与表的开头部分相连
you're waiting for that value so that you can stick it on to the beginning of the List,
但是FOR-EACH不需要等待返回值
whereas for-each doesn't really have any values to wait for.
所以它变成了一个迭代的过程
So that turns out to be an iterative process.
这不是本质
That's not fundamental.
我可以用迭代的方式定义MAP过程
I could have defined MAP so that it's evolved by an iterative process.
只是我没那么做
I just didn't happen to.
学生：将FOR-EACH用在一个列表的列表上的话 我想这是可行的吧？
AUDIENCE: If you were to call for each with a List that had embedded Lists, I imagine it would work, right?
它会对这些内部列表的元素进行处理么？
It would give you the internal elements of each of those internal Lists?
教授：问题是 如果我调用
PROFESSOR: OK, the question is if I call
FOR-EACH或者MAP
for-each or map, for that matter
参数是一个嵌套有一个表的表
with a List that had Lists in it
虽然我们还没有讲过这个 但是那是可行的
although we haven't really looked at that yet--would that work.
答案是肯定的 不过我俩对“可行”的定义可能有些不同
The answer is yes in the sense I mean work and no in the sense that you mean work,
来看一下 如果我给你一个表
because all that-- see if I give you a List,
而在个箭头所指的
where hanging off here is,
不是一个数 而是一个表 或者序对 或者是其它东西
you know, is something that's not a number, maybe another List or you know, another cons or something,
FOR-EACH对表中的每个元素做处理
for-each just says do something to each item in this List.
它会不断地处理表CDR部分
It goes down successively looking at the cdrs.
学生：嗯
AUDIENCE: OK.
教授：对FOR-EACH来说 表中的第一个元素就是这个箭头所指的东西
PROFESSOR: And as far as it's concerned, the first item in this List is whatever is hanging off here.
学生：唔
AUDIENCE: Mhm.
教授：这对于你要完成的任务而言 也许是对的 也许不是
PROFESSOR: That might or might not be the right thing.
学生：所以不能进入子表中
AUDIENCE: So it wouldn't go down into the--
教授：绝对不能
PROFESSOR: Absolutely not.
当然我也可以那样写程序
I could certainly write something else.
你所说的是另一种公共模式 叫做树递归
There's another, what you're looking for is a common pattern of usage called tree recursion,
当你给它一个表 它会不断向深度递归 直到遇到所谓的“树叶”
where you take a List, and you actually go all the way down to the what's called the leaves of the tree.
你可以写出来这个过程 但是它既不是FOR-EACH也不是MAP
And you could write such a thing, but that's not for-each and it's not MAP.
FOR-EACH和MAP都很简单
Remember, these things are really being very simple minded.
好 还有问题么？
OK, no more questions?
好的 大家休息一下吧
All right, let's break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
Henderson-Escher的例子
Henderson Escher Example
教授：我将在本节课余下的时间中 讨论一个实例
PROFESSOR: What I'd like to do now is spend the rest of this time talking about one example,
这个实例 可以充分地总结我们所学的所有东西
and this example, I think, pretty much summarizes everything that we've done up until now:
比如 表结构
all right, and that's List structure
以及抽象的技术
and issues of abstraction,
数据的表示
and representation
和用高阶过程描绘共性
and representation and capturing commonality with higher order procedures,
也会介绍目前为止还没怎么谈论过的
and also is going to introduce something we haven't really talked about a lot yet-- what I said is the major third theme in this course:
也就是这门课的第三大主题
what I said is the major third theme in this course:
元语言抽象
meta-linguistic abstraction,
这种在工程设计中控制复杂度的思想
which is the idea that one of the ways of tackling complexity in engineering design
也就是建立一个合适而强大的语言
is to build a suitable powerful language.
你们或许记得 我说过在这门课程中 你们将要学到的最重要的事情是
You might recall what I said was pretty much the very most important thing that we're going to tell you in this course is that
当我们考察一门语言时 关心的是它的基本元素
when you think about a language, you think about it in terms of what are the primitives;
关心它的组合手段
what are the means of combination--
关心那些让你能够构建更大东西的东西
right, what are the things that allow you to build bigger things;
以及 抽象的方式
and then what are the means of abstraction.
如何取用这些你构造出来的“大东西”
How do you take those bigger things that you've built
并将它们放入“黑盒”中
put black boxes around them
然后用它们来构建更复杂的东西
and use them as elements in making something even more complicated?
我将要介绍的一种语言 就是元语言抽象的一个例子
Now the particular language I'm going to talk about is an example
那是我朋友Peter Handerson发明的
that was made up by a friend of ours called Peter Henderson.
他来自苏格兰的Stirling大学
Peter Henderson is at the University of Stirling in Scotland.
这个语言是用来画这样的图
And what this language is about is making figures that sort of look like this.
这是埃舍尔的木版画 《方形极限》
This is this is a woodcut by Escher called "Square Limit."
正如大家所见 这里面有着很复杂的...图像的递归
You, sort of, see it has this complicated, kind of, recursive, sort of, recursive kind of figure,
其中中间的鱼形图案以自相似的方式
where there's this fish pattern in the middle and things sort of
不断地以更小的形式出现在原来的团案旁边
bleed out smaller and smaller in self similar ways.
总之 Peter Hendersion的语言是用来表述这类图形
Anyway, Peter Henderson's language was for describing figures that look like that
并且设计类似的图形 将它画在显示器上
and designing new ones that look like that and drawing them on a display screen.
这个例子还展示了另外一个主题
There's another theme that we'll see illustrated by this example,
这也是我跟Gerry教授多次强调的
and that's the issue of what Gerry and I have already mentioned a lot:
也就是过程跟数据之间没有本质的区别
that there's no real difference, in some sense, between procedures and data.
不管如何 我希望今早课程结束后
And anyway I hope by the end of this morning, if you're not already,
你们能将过程和数据当作一回事儿
you will be completely confused about what the difference between procedures and data are,
即使现在你们还将它们区别对待
if you're not confused about that already.
那么 先让我们看一下Peter的语言
Well in any case, let's start describing Peter's language.
我先告诉你们基本元素是什么
I should start by telling you what the primitives are.
这个语言非常简单 因为它的基本元素只有一个
This language is very simple because there's only one primitive.
这个基本元素不是大家想象的那样
A primitive is not quite what you think it is.
它唯一的基本元素叫做"图像"
There's only one primitive called a picture,
但此“图像”非彼“图像”
and a picture is not quite what you think it is.
具体地来说
Here's an example.
这是George的图像
This is a picture of George.
我们的想法是
The idea is that
在这个语言中的图像是这样一个东西
a picture in this language is going to be something
它能在你指定的一个矩形里画出一个缩放好图像
that draws a figure scaled to fit a rectangle that you specify.
这里大家看到的强调线
So here you see emphasis line
是这个矩形的轮廓 但不是图像的一部分
is outline of a rectangle, that's not really part of the picture,
但是一旦指定一个矩形区域 图像会以以填充的方式绘制满区域
but the picture-- you'll give it a rectangle, and it will draw this figure scaled to fit the rectangle.
比如 这个是George 在这里 这个也是George
So for example, there's George, and here, this is also George.
它是同一个图像 只是缩放程度不同
It's the same picture, right, just scaled to fit a different rectangle.
这是“胖”George的版本
Here's George as a fat kid.
这个也是George
That's the same George.
这是同一个图形
It's all the same figure.
这个语言中 这三个都是同一个图像
All of these three things are the same picture in this language.
仅仅是给了不同的矩形区域让它来填充
I'm just giving it different rectangles to scale itself in.
这就是基本元素
OK, those are the primitives. That is the primitive.
现在 我们来讨论元素组合和操作
Now let's start talking about the means of combination and the operations.
比如 这里有一个叫做旋转的操作
There is, for example, an operation called Rotate.
如果我有一个图像 “旋转”操作就是
And what Rotate does is, if I have a picture,
先假定有一个里面有个“A”的矩形
say a picture that draws an "A" in some rectangle that I give it,
而旋转90度的操作则会
the Rotate of that--say the Rotate by 90 degrees would,
在一个给定的矩形内 绘制同样的图像
if I give it a rectangle, draw the same image,
但是 会缩放图像以适应矩形
but again, scaled to fit that rectangle.
这个就是旋转90度
So that's Rotate by 90 degrees.
另一个操作是“翻转” 可以水平翻转也可以竖直翻转
There's another operation called Flip that can flip something, either horizontally or vertically.
就是这些操作了
All right, so those are, sort of, operations,
或者你可以把它们认为是组合一个元素的各种方式
or you can think of those as means of combination of one element.
我可以把它们混合起来
I can put things together.
我们有一种叫BESIDE的操作
There's a means of combination called Beside,
它做的事情是 给定两个图像A、B --
and what Beside does: it'll take two pictures, let's say A and B--
这里图像是指能在指定的矩形中画一个图案的东西 --
and by picture I mean something that's going to draw an image in a specified rectangle--
BESIDE将会做的事情
and what Beside will do--
类似于调用(BESIDE A B S) 其中S是一个数
I have to say, Beside of A and B, the side of two pictures and some number, s.
是一个在0到1之间的数
And s will be a number between zero and one.
BESIDE绘制像这样的图像
And Beside will draw a picture that looks like this.
以给定的矩形为基础 但会将基底缩放S
It will take the rectangle you give it and scale its base by s.
这里S是0.5
Say s is 0.5.
在这里 它会在这里画第一个图案
And then over here it will draw-- it'll put the first picture, and over here it'll put the second picture.
在这里画第二个图案
and over here it'll put the second picture.
又比如说 我另设一个S的值
Or for instance if I gave it a different value of s,
比如调用(BESIDE A B 0.25)
Or for instance if I gave it a different value of s, if I said Beside with a 0.25,
效果相同 只不过A更瘦了
it would do the same thing, except the A would be much skinnier.
而B是这样的
So it would draw something like that.
这就是组合手段之一：BESIDE
So there's a means of combination Beside,
类似地 ABOVE方法在竖直方向上做这种操作
and similarly there's an Above, which does the same thing except it puts them vertically instead of horizontally.
我们来看一下
Well let's look at that.
这是George和他的"弟弟"
All right, there's George and his kid brother,
这是通过将George放在一旁
which is, right, constructed by taking George and putting him Beside
George与空图像的上下组合放在另一旁
The Above, taking the empty picture, and there's a thing called the empty picture,
这样做的意图很明显
which does the obvious thing--
空图像放在了另一个George的上面
putting the empty picture above a copy of George,
合成的图像又放在了George的旁边
and then putting that whole thing Beside George.
这个是图像P
Here's something called P which is,
像之前一样 是George和翻转后George的BESIDE组合
which is, again, George Beside Flipping George,
这里 我们做的是水平翻转
I think, horizontally in this case,
然后整体旋转180度
Rotating the whole result 180 degrees
然后调用BESIDE让它们组合在一起 系数是0.5
putting them Beside one another with the basic rectangle divided at 0.5,
这样 我创建了图像P
right, and I can call that P.
然后使用图像P
And then I can take P,
与它的翻转图像做ABOVE操作 形成图像Q
And then I can take P, and put it above the Flipped copy of itself, and I can call that Q.
请注意 我们是如何快速地增加复杂度
Notice how rapidly that we've built up complexity,
转瞬之间 我们使用George组合得到了Q 这说明了什么？
just in, you know, 15 seconds, you've gotten from George to that thing Q. Why is that?
为什么我们可以做得如此迅速呢?
How are how we able to do that so fast?
答案是闭包性质
The answer is the closure property.
这是因为 当我将两个图像做BESIDE操作后
See, it's the fact that when I take a picture and put it Beside another picture,
得到的也是图像
that's then, again, a picture
我可以继续执行 ROTATE FLIP 或者 ABOVE操作
that I can go and Rotate and Flip or put Above something else.
而操作的结果P
Right, and when I take that element P,
BESIDE FLIP ROTATE操作的结果也是一个图像
which is the Beside or the Flip or the Rotate of something, that's, again, a picture.
在这种组合方法下 图像的世界是封闭的
Right, the world of pictures is closed under those means of combination.
所以 任何时候我都可以
So whenever I have something,
以一个东西为基本元素 去构造别的东西
I can turn right around and use that as an element in something else.
这个例子比表和线段更直观
So maybe better than List and segments,
它揭示了 我们如何用封闭的操作 快速增加复杂度
that just gives you an image for how fast you can build up complexity, because operations are closed.
在构建更多东西之前
OK, well before we go on with building more things,
我们先来看看这个语言是如何实现的
let's talk about how this language is actually implemented.
其中基本的一个元素
The basic element that sits under the table here
是一个称作“矩形”的东西
is a thing called a rectangle,
所谓的矩形就是
and what a rectangle is going to be,
它有一个原点
it's a thing that specified by an origin
原点是一个向量 用以说明矩形是从哪开始
that's going to be some vector that says where the rectangle starts.
至于其它的向量
And then there's going to be some other vector
我们称其为矩形的水平分量
that I'm going to call the horizontal part of the rectangle,
还有就是矩形的竖直分量
and another vector called the vertical part of the rectangle.
这就是构成矩形的三个基本元素
And those three pieces are the elements:
两个向量用作
where the lower vertex is,
计算左上角和右下角的顶点坐标
how you get to the next vertex over here, and how you get to the vertex over there.
这三个向量确定了一个矩形
The three vectors specify a rectangle.
为了构建矩形 我们假设
Now to actually build rectangles, what I'll assume is
假设有个“构建矩形”的构造函数
that we have a constructor called "make rectangle,"
也就是MAKE-RECT
or "make-rect,"
以及选择函数 HORIZ、VERT 和 ORIGIN
and selectors for horiz and vert and origin
用于取得对应的矩形属性
that get out the pieces of that rectangle.
我们知道有很多方法可以实现它
And well, you know a lot of ways you can do this now.
可以用序对或者表 或者其它东西
You can do it by using pairs in some way or other standard List or not.
但是 这些东西的实现是George的事
But in any case, the implementation of these things, that's George's problem.
这是一个数据表示的问题
It's just a data representation problem.
现在我们假设已经有了这些矩形了
So let's assume we have these rectangles to work with.
好的 现在来看我们接下来要做的事情
OK. Now the idea of this, remember what's got to happen.
我们需要关心如何取用图像
Somehow we have to worry about taking the figure
将它缩放以适应你给定的矩形
and scaling it to fit some rectangle that you give it,
我们要来安排这些事
that's the basic thing you have to arrange,
来完成图像的缩放
that these pictures can do.
有哪些思路呢？
How do we think about that?
一种想法是：无论何时给定一个矩形
Well, one way to think about that is that any time I give you a rectangle,
无论何时给定一个矩形 也就是说
Any time I gave you a rectangle, that defines,
这在某种意义上是把正方形转换成矩形
that defines,in some sense, a transformation from the standard square into that rectangle.
也就是说
Let me say what I mean.
我所谓的正方形
By the standard square, I'll mean something,
它的坐标是(0,0)、(1,0)、(0,1)和(1,1)
which is a square whose coordinates are 0,0, and 1,0, and 0,1 and 1,1.
我们有一些显而易见的缩放变换
And there's some sort of the obvious scaling transformation,
可以把这个映射成这个 把这个映射成这个
which maps this to that and this to that,
并且 把所有的东西统一地拉伸
and sort of, stretches everything uniformly.
我们将这样的一条的线段
So we take a line segment like this
将它最终映射到像那样的一条线段
and end up mapping it to a line segment like that,
而点(X,Y)变成了这里的另外一个点
so some point (x,y) goes to some other point up there.
这个不紧要 会点向量运算 就能写出变换公式
And although it's not important, with a little vector algebra, you could write that formula.
初始点(X,Y)将会变换到的点的坐标是
The thing that (x,y) goes to, the point that (x,y) goes to is
以矩形原点为基础做向量加法
gotten by taking the origin of the rectangle and then adding that as a vector to--
加上 初始点X坐标 一个介于0和1之间的值
well, take x, the x coordinate, which is something between zero and one,
并乘上矩形的水平向量
multiply that by the horizontal vector of the rectangle;
再加上初始点的Y坐标 也是一个介于0和1的值
and take the y coordinate, which is also something between zero and one
并乘上矩形的竖直向量
and multiply that by the vertical vector of the rectangle.
这是简单的线性代数
That's just a little linear algebra.
这个就是正确的变换公式
Anyway, that's the formula, which is the right obvious transformation
它将方形中的物件转化到对应矩形中
that takes things into the unit square, into the interior of that rectangle.
现在 我们把它看作是一个过程
OK well, let's actually look at that as a procedure.
我们想要得到的是
So what we want is
由一个单位正方形到特定矩形的
the thing which tells us that particular transformation
特定变换过程
that a rectangle defines.
这个过程具体是这样的
So here's the procedure.
我叫它COORD-MAP
I'll call it coordinate-map.
COORD-MAP以一个矩形作为参数
Coordinate-map is the thing that takes as its argument a rectangle
它返回一个以点为参数的过程
and returns for you a procedure on points.
每个矩形 都对应一个变换点(X, Y)坐标的过程
Right, so for each rectangle you get a way of transforming a point (x,y) into that rectangle.，
是怎么得到的呢？
And how do you get it?
就如黑板上的Lisp代码所示
Well I just--  writing in Lisp what I wrote there on the blackboard--
我让矩形的原点加上——
I add to the origin of the rectangle
首先是 矩形水平部分
the result of adding-- I take the horizontal part of the rectangle;
按照点POINT的X坐标缩放
I scale that by the x coordinate of the point.
然后是 矩形竖直部分
I take the vertical vector of the rectangle.
按照点POINT的Y坐标缩放
I scale that by the y coordinate of the point,
然后把它们三个加到一起
and then add all those three things up.
这个过程就是这样
That's the procedure.
这就是我将要应用在点POINT上的过程
That is the procedure that I'm going to apply to a point.
这个过程由每个矩形自己生成
And this whole thing is generated for each rectangle.
每个矩形对应了一个定义在点集上的过程 COORD-MAP
So any rectangle defines a Coordinate-MAP, which is a procedure on points.
比如说 这里的George
All right, so for example, George here,
最初的George 可能是我在单位正方形中通过线段绘制的
my original George, might have been something that I specified by segments in the unit square,
而当我把它应用到一个新的矩形中
and then for each rectangle I give this thing,
我将会在新矩形中画出组成George的那些线段来
I'm going to draw those segments inside that rectangle.
我是怎么做的呢？
How actually do I do that?
我枚举原始George中的每条线段
Well I take each segment in my original reference George that was specified,
我对每条线段的终点
and to each of the end points of those segments,
应用目标矩形对应的COORD-MAP过程
I applied the COORDINATE-MAP of the particular rectangle I want to draw it in.
比如下面的这个矩形
So for example, this lower rectangle,
这个胖George 有它对应的COORD-MAP
this George as a fat kid rectangle, has its COORDINATE-MAP.
如果我要绘制这个图像
And if I want to draw this image,
需要做的就是对这里的每条线段 比如这条
And if I want to draw this image, what I do is for each segment here, say for this segment,
用COORD-MAP变换这个点 同时变换这个点
I transformed that point by the coordinate MAP, transform that point by the coordinate MAP.
我就得到了这两个点
That will give me this point and that point
就可以将在两点之间画线
and draw the segment between them.
这就是核心思路
Right, that's the idea.
那么如果我给一个不同的矩形 比如这个
Right, and if I give it a different rectangle like this one,
得到的是不同的COORD-MAP
that's a different coordinate-MAP,
因此我得到这些线段的不同图像
so I get a different image of those line segments.
基本图像又该如何表示呢？
Well how do we actually get a picture to start with?
可以用线段组成的表来表示
I can build a picture to start with out of a List of line segments initially.
这是用于构建我所谓的“基本图像”的过程
Here's a procedure that builds what I'll call a primitive picture,
意思是 没有用BESIDE ROTATE等操作
meaning one I, sort of, got that didn't come out of Beside or Rotate or something.
它以由线段组成的表为参数
It starts with a List of line segments,
代码具体行为如下
And now it does what I said.
图像会是什么样子呢？
What's a picture have to be?
首先 它是一个根据矩形定义的过程
First of all it's a procedure that's defined on rectangles.
这个过程做什么呢？
What does it do?
对于由线段组成的表中每个元素
It says for each-- this is going to be a List of line segments--
表中的每条线段S
for each segment, for each s, which is a segment in this List of segments,
都绘制了一条线
well it draws a line.
它画什么样的线段呢？
What line does it draw?
先得到线段的起点
It gets the start point of that segment,
用对应的COORD-MAP对其做变换
transforms that by the coordinate MAP of the rectangle.
这是我们想要的第一个点
That's the first new point it wants to do.
然后对线段终点做COORD-MAP操作
Then it takes the endpoint of the segment, transforms that by the coordinate MAP of the rectangle,
并将两点连线
and then draws a line between.
我们假设在屏幕上绘制线段是基本操作
Let's assume drawline is some primitive that's built into the system
已经在系统中实现了
that actually draws a line on the display.
通过COORD-MAP变换了线段终点
All right, so it transforms the endpoints by the coordinate MAP of the rectangle,
再把起点和终点连线
draws a line between them,
对表中每一条线段S都执行这样的操作
does that for each s in this List of segments.
请注意 图像就是一个以矩形为参数的过程
And now remember again, a picture is a procedure that takes a rectangle as argument.
所以当你给图像一个矩形时 它就像这样绘制线段
So when you hand it a rectangle, this is what it does: draws those lines.
那好 我应该如何使用它呢？
All right, so there's-- how would I actually use this thing?
我来说得具体一点
Let's make it a little bit more concrete.
就比如说 (DEFINE R (MAKE-RECT ...))
Right, I would say for instance, define R to be make-rectangle of some stuff,
这里需要用MAKE-VECTOR来构造一些向量
and I'd have to specify some vectors here using make-vector.
然后定义G为 (DEFINE G (MAKE-PICT ...))
And then I could say, define say, G to be make-picture, and then some stuff.
我要在这里使用MAKE-SEGMENT来构建线段组成的表
And what I'd have to specify here is a List of line segments, right, using make segment.
MAKE-SEGMENT由向量构成 向量由点构成
Make-segment might be made out of vectors, and vectors might be made out of points.
如果我想在一个矩形中呈现图像G
And then if I actually wanted to see the image of G inside a rectangle,
注意 图像是一个过程 它接受一个矩形作为参数
well a picture is a procedure that takes a rectangle as argument.
所以 如果我调用(G R)
So if I then called G with an input of R,
那么无论G是什么 都会在矩形R中绘制出来
that would cause whatever image G is worrying about to be drawn inside the rectangle R.
这就是我们如何使用它
Right, so that's how you'd use that.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
Henderson-Escher的例子
Henderson Escher Example
教授：为什么我说这个例子很好呢？
PROFESSOR: Well why is it that I say this example is nice?
也许你们不这么认为
You probably don't think it's nice.
你们可能觉得它很奇怪
You probably think it's more weird than nice.
用来矩形做复杂变换的过程来表示图像 确实奇怪
Right, representing these pictures as procedures, which do complicated things with rectangles.
那么 它好在哪里呢？
So why is it nice?
原因就是
The reason it's nice
一旦你按这种方法实现了基本元素
is that once you've implemented the primitives in this way,
组合的手段就是构造Lisp过程
the means of combination just fall out by implementing procedures.
我给你们演示一下
Let me show you what I mean.
假设我想实现BESIDE
Suppose we want to implement Beside.
我要做的是 假设有个叫P1的图像
So I'd like to--  suppose I've got a picture. Let's call it P1.
一定要记得：图像本质上是一个过程
P1 is going to be-- and now remember what a picture really is.
当你传递给它一个矩形
It's a thing that if you hand it some rectangle,
它会在你给定的矩形中绘制图形
it will cause an image to be drawn in whatever rectangle you hand it.
假设P2是另一个图像 你传递给它一个矩形
And suppose P2 two is some other picture, and you hand that a rectangle.
无论给它什么矩形 它都会绘制一些图案
And whatever rectangle you hand it, it draws some picture.
现在 我想实现(BESIDE P1 P2 A) A是缩放因子
And now if I'd like to implement Beside of P1 and P2 with a scale factor A,
会得到什么呢？
well what does that have to be?
我们会得到一个图像
That's gotta be a picture.
也就是说你传给它一个矩形 它就会在其中绘图
It's gotta be a thing that you handed a rectangle and draw something in that rectangle.
如果我们在一个矩形中执行BESIDE操作
So if hand Beside this rectangle--
比如这个矩形
let's hand it a rectangle.
要做什么呢？
Well what's it going to do?
一部分比例是A 另一部分是1-A
It's going to take this rectangle and split it into two
at a ratio of A and one minus A.
现在 我们就有了两个矩形
And it will say, oh sure, now I've got two rectangles.
然后先让P1在这个矩形中绘制
And now it goes off to P1 and says P1, well draw yourself in this rectangle,
然后让P2在这个矩形中绘制
and goes off to P2, and says, P2, fine, draw yourself in this rectangle.
BESIDE仅仅需要计算出这些矩形来
The only computation it has to do is figure out what these rectangles are.
由于矩形是由原点、水平向量和竖直向量组成
Remember a rectangle is specified by an origin and a horizontal vector and a vertical vector.
BESIDE操作需要计算出这些要素
so it's got to figure out what these things are.
所以对第一个矩形来说 原点变成了矩形的原点
So for this first rectangle, the origin turns out to be the origin of the original rectangle,
竖直向量与原矩形相同 不发生变化
and the vertical vector is the same as the vertical vector of the original rectangle.
水平向量是原始矩形的水平向量缩放A倍得到的
The horizontal vector is the horizontal vector of the original rectangle scaled by A.
这就是第一个矩形
And that's the first rectangle.
第二个矩形的原点是
The second rectangle, the origin
原矩形的原点加上矩形的水平向量缩放A倍
The second rectangle, the origin is the original origin plus that horizontal vector scaled by A.
第二个矩形的水平向量是
The horizontal vector of the second rectangle is
除去前一个矩形水平向量所余下的部分
the rest of the horizontal vector of the first one,
也就是(1-A)*H H是原矩形的水平向量
which is 1 minus A times the original H,
它的竖直向量还是V
and the vertical vector is still v.
基本上 BESIDE就是构造这两个矩形
But basically it goes and constructs these two rectangles,
但重要的是 一旦构造好这些矩形
and the important point is having constructed the rectangles,
它就能让P1、P2在正确的位置绘制
it says OK, p1, you draw yourself in there, and p2, you draw yourself in there,
这就是BESIDE需要做的全部工作
and that's all Beside has to do.
我们看一下代码
All right, let's look at that piece of code.
这是BESIDE
Beside
(BESIDE P1 P2 A) A是缩放比例
Beside of a picture and another picture with some scaling ratio
因为该过程返回图像 所以结果是一个以矩形为参数的过程
is first of all, since it's a picture, a procedure that's going to take a rectangle as argument.
它做什么呢？
What's it going to do?
它让P1在某个矩形中绘制 P2在另一个矩形中绘制
It says, p1 draw yourself in some rectangle and p2 draw yourself in some other rectangle.
现在这些矩形又是什么呢?
And now what are those rectangles?
就在这里计算
Well here's the computation.
它创建了一个矩形
It makes a rectangle,
用的是我刚才在黑板上写的几何公式 这是矩形的原点
and this is the algebra I just did on the board: the origin, something;
矩形的水平向量
the horizontal vector, something;
还有矩形的竖直向量
and the vertical vector, something.
对于P2
For p2
矩形需要不同的原点 水平向量和竖直向量
And for p2, the rectangle it wants has some other origin and horizontal vector and vertical vector.
但重要的是
But the important point
BESIDE只是将这两个矩形分别传递给了P1和P2而已
is that all it's saying is, p1, go do your thing in one rectangle, and p2, go do your thing in another rectangle.
这就是BESIDE所需要做的
That's all the Beside has to do.
好 ROTATE也很类似
OK, similarly Rotate--
假设我有一个图像A
see if I have this picture A,
我想让它旋转90度
and I want to look at say rotating A by 90 degrees,
这意味着 给定这个矩形
what that should mean is, well take this rectangle,
它有原点、水平向量和竖直向量
which is origin and horizontal vector and vertical vector,
现在假设已经有了这样的矩形
and now pretend that it's really the rectangle that looks like this,
这个矩形的原点、水平向量和竖直向量在这里
which has an origin and a horizontal vector up here, and a vertical vector there,
然后在矩形里各自绘制自己
and now draw yourself with respect to that rectangle.
我们来看看代码
Let me show you that as a procedure.
那么 ROTATE90过程
All right, so we'll Rotate 90 of the picture,
返回的也是一个以矩形为参数的过程
because again, a procedure for rectangle,
它就是将图像绘制在一个特定矩形中
which says, OK picture, draw yourself in some rectangle;
这个几何公式就是这个矩形的变换规则
and then this algebra is the transformation on the rectangle.
这句代码让矩形看起来像向侧面的
It's the one which makes it look like the rectangle is sideways,
原点在别的地方 竖直向量在别的地方
the origin is someplace else and the vertical vector is someplace else,
水平向量在别的地方 竖直向量在别的地方
and the horizontal vector is someplace else, and vertical vector is someplace else.
再次注意 这里的关键是
OK, again notice, the crucial thing that's going on here
关键是使用过程来表示图像 使其自动地具有闭包性质
is you're using the representation of pictures as procedures to automatically get the closure property,
这是因为 实际上 BESIDE只是接受并使用P1
because what happens is, Beside just has this thing p1.
BESIDE并不关心它是一个基本图像还是一些线段
Beside doesn't care if that's a primitive picture or it's line segments
或者P1还是ABOVE、BESIDE、ROTATE等操作的结果
if p1 is, itself, the result of doing Aboves or Besides or Rotates.
关于P1 BESIDE需要知道的就是
All Beside has to know about, say, p1
给P1传递一个矩形 就会导致某物的绘制
p1 is that if you hand p1 a rectangle, it will cause something to be drawn.
在这个层面上 BESIDE并不关心P1是如何完成绘制
And above that level, Beside just doesn't-- it's none of its business how p1 accomplishes that drawing.
我们使用过程来表示图像 以保持它的闭包性质
All right, so you're using the procedural representation to ensure this closure.
将图像实现为过程 使得组合的方法变得
So implementing pictures as procedures makes these means of combination,
变得简单而优雅
both pretty simple and also, I think, elegant.
但这并不是点睛之笔
But that's not the real punchline.
点睛之笔来自于这门语言中抽象的方法
The real punchline comes when you look at the means of abstraction in this language.
我们做了些什么？
Because what have we done?
我们把组合的方法实现为了过程
We've implemented the means of combination themselves as procedures.
这也就意味着 当我们对这个语言进行抽象时
And what that means is that when we go to abstract in this language,
Lisp提供的 操作过程的一切方法
everything that Lisp supplies us for manipulating procedures
都可以自动地在这个图像语言中使用
automatically available to do things in this picture language.
与其用术语“这个语言以Lisp实现” — 虽然确实如此
The technical term I want to say is not only is this language implemented in Lisp, obviously it is,
我想描述为“这个语言嵌入于Lisp”
but the language is nicely embedded in Lisp.
也就是说 通过像这样将语言嵌入
What I mean is by embedding the language in this way,
可以以扩展的形式 自动地获得Lisp的所有力量
all the power of Lisp is automatically available as an extension to whatever you want to do.
这又是什么意思呢？
And what do I mean by that?
举个例子 假设我想用A B C D四副图像做东西
Example: say, suppose I want to make a thing that takes four pictures A, B, C and D,
让它们呈现像这样的格局
and makes a configuration that looks like this.
可以将其称为FOUR-PICT格局
Well you might call that, you know, four pictures or something, four-pict configuration.
我该如何做呢？
How do I do that?
我可以很容易的做到这些
Well I can obviously do that.
写个过程 让B和D做ABOVE
I just write a procedure that takes B above D
A和C做ABOVE
and A above C
得到的结果做BESIDE
and puts those things beside each other.
我自然地拥有Lisp组合过程的能力
So I automatically have Lisp's ability to do procedure composition.
这不需要我为图像语言做些特殊处理
And I didn't have to make that specifically in the picture language.
事实上 这些组合本身就是过程
It's automatic from the fact that the means of combination are themselves procedures.
假设我想做一些更复杂的事情
Or suppose I wanted to do something a little bit more complicated.
我想为这里的每一个传递一个参数
I wanted to put in a parameter so that for each of these,
我可以独立地做旋转90度的操作
I could independently specify a rotation by 90 degrees.
这只需要我在这个过程中加入一个参数
That's just putting a parameter in the procedure.
它自然而然就有了这样的功能
It's automatically there.
它自动地嵌入进去了
Right, it automatically comes from the embedding.
甚至 假设我想使用递归
Or even more, suppose I wanted to, you know, use recursion.
我们看一下图像递归组合的方法
Let's look at a recursive means of combination on pictures.
定义--看看你们能理解这个不
I could say define-- let's see if you can figure out what this one is--
(DEFINE (RIGHT-PUSH PICT N A))
suppose I say define what it means to right-push a picture,
RIGHT-PUSH需要图片P 整数N和缩放因数A
right-push a picture and some integer N and some scale factor A.
定义是：如果N为0 那么返回图像P
I'll define this to say if N equals 0, then the answer is the picture.
否则 就-- 哦 这里是P
Otherwise I'm going to put-- oops, name change: P.
否则 我用图形P做BESIDE操作
Otherwise, I'm going to take P and put it beside
BESIDE的另一个操作数是(RIGHT-PUSH P (- N 1) A)的结果
the results of recursively right-pushing P with N minus 1 and A and use a scale factor of A. OK,
如果N为0 就返回P 否则就对P进行A倍缩放
so if N 0 , it's P. Otherwise I put P with a scale factor of A--
抱歉 我这里代码没对齐
I'm sorry I didn't align this right--
递归地调用(RIGHT-PUSH P (- N 1) A) 将结果用BESIDE连接
recursively beside the result of right-pushing P, N minus 1 times with a scale factor of A.
这就是一种递归组合方法
There's a recursive means of combination.
调用的结果会是怎样的？
What's that look like?
我们来看看
Well, here's what it looks like.
这是(RIGHT-PUSH GEORGE 2 0.75)的结果
There's George right-pushed against himself twice with a scale factor of 0.75.
这个是从什么地方来的呢？
Where'd that come from?
我是如何想象出这些递归来的呢？
How did I get all this fancy recursion?
答案是无意识的 绝对是无意识的
And the answer is just automatic, absolutely automatic.
由于它们都是过程 而嵌入的目标系统中允许定义递归过程
Since these are procedures, the embedding says, well sure, I can define recursive procedures.
我不必自己去做
I didn't have to arrange that.
当然 我们可以模仿这个方法做些更复杂的事
And of course, we can do more complicated things of the same sort.
我可以定义做UP-PUSH的过程
I could make something that does an up-push.
对 它可以递归地把图片放在原来的上面
Right, that sort of goes like this, by recursively putting something above.
我也可以用这种策略来做些其它事
Or I could make something that, sort of, was this scheme.
给定一个图像
I might start out with a picture
然后递归地把它放在原图片的旁边和上面
and then, sort of, recursively both push it aside and above
这里再放一些别的
and that might put something there.
然后我把同样递归的图像放在这里
And then up here I put the same recursive thing,
我可以用这个来终止
and I might end up with something like this.
这个过程比RIGHT-PUSH复杂一点 但也不算太多
Right, so there's a procedure that's a little bit more complicated than right-push but not much.
在BESIDE的基础上 我多加了一个ABOVE操作
I just do an Above and a Beside, rather than just a Beside.
如果我把它应用于四张放在一起的图像上
Now if I take that and apply that with the idea of putting four pictures together,
这样做当然没问题
which I can surely do;
我把它应用于我们之前定义的Q上
and I go and I apply that to Q, which we defined before, right,
我得到的是这个玩意儿
what I end up with this is this thing,
"图像Q的方形极限" 做了两次
which is, sort of, the square limit of Q, done twice.
好 现在我们将其与Escher的"方形极限"对比一下
Right, and then we can compare that with Escher's "Square Limit."
可以看到 这都是基于同样的思想
And you see, it's sort of the same idea.
当然 Escher的图像更加漂亮一些
Escher's is, of course, much, much prettier.
如果我们回过头审视George
If we go back and look at George, right, if we go look at George here--
我最开始用的是非常随意的设计
see, I started with a fairly arbitrary design
用了George的图像 做了一些操作
this picture of George and did things with it.
我们再看看Escher的图片
Right, whereas if we go look at the Escher picture, right,
Escher的图片不是随意设计的
the Escher picture is not an arbitrary design.
这个图案非常精妙
It's this very, very clever thing,
当我们把鱼身
so that when you take this fish body
把鱼身旋转并放缩 就会优美地变成下一条鱼
and Rotate it and shrink it down, it bleeds into the next one really nicely.
当然我没有刻意处理过George
And of course with George, I didn't really do anything like that.
就图像George来说
So if we look at George,
也有一些地方匹配 但不够好 比较随意
right, there's a little bit of match up, but not very nice, and it's pretty arbitrary.
顺便说下 一个好的程序
One very nice project, by the way,
应该有个过程 能接受像这里George一样的基本图像
would be to write a procedure that could take some basic figure like this George thing
然后调整其中的线段终点
and start moving the ends of the lines around,
这样可以得到一个好看的图像
so you got a really nice one
在做“方形极限”应该注意这些
when you went and did that "Square Limit" process.
这是一个非常值得思考的事情
That'd be a really nice thing to think about.
同时 我还可以进行组合
Well so, we can combine things.
我们还可以使用递归过程
We can recursive procedures.
我们可以自然而然地做任何事情
We can do all kinds of things, and that's all automatic.
重点在于 在语言中实际实现另一个语言
Right, the important point, the difference between merely implementing something in a language
在语言中嵌入另一个语言的差异
and embedding something in the language,
这可以让你不丢失原有语言的能力 而Lisp强大之处在于
so that you don't lose the original power of the language, and what Lisp is great at,
Lisp是一个强悍的语言 可以处理任何特定问题
see Lisp is a lousy language for doing any particular problem.
把你想要的语言嵌入到Lisp中才是真的好
What it's good for is figuring out the right language that you want and embedding that in Lisp.
这才是这种设计方法的真正力量
That's the real power of this approach to design.
我们可以深入一下
Of course, we can go further.
在Lisp中我们还可以做些其它的事
See, you saw the other thing that we can do in Lisp
就是将通用方法抽象成高阶过程
is capture general methods of doing things as higher order procedures.
在我画那些图像时 你们可能已经发现
And you probably just from me drawing it got the idea that right-push
RIGHT-PUSH和类似的过程 就是一直在上面放东西
and the analogous thing where you push something up and up and up and up
而这个CORNER-PUSH则是一种一般性思想的泛化
and this corner push thing are all generalizations of a common kind of idea.
为了演示并让大家熟悉
So just to illustrate and give you practice in looking at a
使用廊腰缦回的高阶过程
at a fairly convoluted use of higher order procedures,
我给大家示范一下“递归地重复某种组合方法”的一般性思想
let me show you the general idea of pushing some means of combination to recursively repeat it.
这个例子可以说明一切
So here's a good one to puzzle out.
我们可以定义一个依赖于具体组合方式的PUSH过程
We'll define it what it means to push using a means of combination.
COMB的取值可以是BESIDE或ABOVE等
Comb is going to be something like the Beside or Above.
过程的体是什么呢？
Well what's that going to be.
它返回一个过程 想一想BESIDE实际上是什么
That's going to be a procedure, remember what Beside actually was, right.
它接受一个图像
It took a picture,
哦  它接受两个图像和一个缩放因数
took two pictures and a scale factor.
利用这个过程 定义一个接受层数、图像和缩放因数的过程
Using that I produced something that took a level number and a picture and a scale factor,
我称之为RIGHT-PUSH
that I called right-push.
这个过程接受 图像PICT 层数N和缩放因数A
So this is going to be something that takes a picture, a level number and a scale factor, and it's going to say--
我要做一些重复操作
I'm going to do some repeated operation.
我会重复应用一个接受一个图像P的过程
I'm going to repeatedly apply the procedure which takes a picture
并把组合的方式应用在
and applies the means of combination
应用在图像PICT和在这里接受的图像P以及缩放因数A
to the picture and the original picture and the one I took in here and the scale factor,
我要重复应用这个过程N次
and I do the thing which repeats this procedure N times,
我则是把这整个过程应用在原图片PICT上
and I apply that whole thing to my original picture.
虽然之前没提过 这里的REPEATED也是一个高阶过程
Repeated here, in case you haven't seen it, is another higher order procedure
它接受一个过程P和一个数字N
that takes a procedure and a number
它返回另一个过程：将给定的过程P重复应用N次的过程
and returns for you another procedure that applies this procedure N times.
可能有些人已经在练习中编写过REPEATED了
And I think some of you have already written repeated as an exercise,
如果还没做的话 这是理解和练习高阶过程的好机会
but if you haven't, it's a very good exercise in thinking about higher order procedures.
无论如何 我将把REPEATED过程的结果应用到PICT上
But in any case, the result of this repeated is what I apply to picture.
定义好PUSH后 这就
And having done that, that's going to capture the --
这就是从BESIDE、RIGHT-PUSH中总结出来的一般性思想
that is the thing, the way I got from the idea of Beside to the idea of right-push
现在 我就可以把RIGHT-PUSH定义为 用BESIDE来做PUSH操作
So having done that, I could say define right-push to be push of Beside.
我也可以把UP-PUSH定义为 用ABOVE来做PUSH操作
Or if I say, define up-push to be push of Above
类似地 CORNER-PUSH就是用BESIDE和ABOVE的适当组合做PUSH操作
I'd get the analogous thing or define corner-push to be push of some appropriate thing that did both the Beside and Above,
我可以用任何东西做PUSH操作
or I could push anything.
嗯 如果你还不太理解LAMBDA的话 可以参考这个例子
Anyway this is, if you're having trouble with lambdas, this is an excellent exercise in figuring out what this means.
我们可以从这个例子中学到很多东西
OK, well there's a lot to learn from this example.
我主要想要介绍的是在一个语言中嵌入另一个语言
The main point I've been welling on is the notion of nicely embedding a language inside another language.
这样 母体语言--本例中是Lisp--的所有能力
Right, so that all the power of this language like Lisp of the surrounding language
可以作为你所构建语言的一种扩展而取得
is still accessible to you and appears as a natural extension of the language that you built.
这个例子很好地展示了这点
That's one thing that this example shows very well.
另外 当我们回过头去思考
Another thing is, if you go back and think about that,
什么是过程 什么是数据
what's procedures and what's data.
在这里 天啊 发生了什么
You know, by the time we get up to here, my God, what's going on.
在这里 这是一个过程 它接受一个图像和一个参数
I mean, this is some procedure, and it takes a picture and an argument,
但是 什么是图像呢？
and what's a picture.
请回想 图像本身 就是一个以矩形为参数的过程
Well, a picture itself, as you remember, was a procedure, and that took a rectangle.
这个矩形是某种抽象
And a rectangle is some abstraction.
我希望你们现在能彻底明白
And I hope now that by now you're completely lost
系统中什么是过程 什么是数据
as to the question of what in the system is procedure and what's data.
我们发现 它们没有任何区别
You see, there isn't any difference.
真的没有区别
There really isn't.
你可以认为图像有时候是过程 有时候是数据
And you might think of a picture sometimes as a procedure and sometimes as data,
但是 这只是让你容易理解的一种方法
but that's just, sort of, you know, making you feel comfortable.
这有一定道理 也没有道理
It's really both in some sense or neither in some sense.
关于系统的结构 一种更普遍的观点将其视作创建一种语言
OK, there's a more general point about the structure of the system as creating a language,
将工程设计过程看作是创建一门语言
viewing the engineering design process as one of creating language or
准确来说 是创建各种层次的语言
or rather one of creating a sort of sequence of layers of language.
众所周知 有一种方法学 或者叫做“神话学”
You see, there's this methodology, or maybe I should say mythology,
姑且叫做软件“工程”
that's, sort of, charitably called software, quote, engineering.
它声称 你要先计算出你的任务
All right, and what does it say, it's says well, you go and you figure out your task,
精确且正确地计算出你的任务
and you figure out exactly what you want to do.
一但你搞清楚要做的东西
And once you figure out exactly what you want to do,
你把它划分为三个子任务
you find out that it breaks out into three sub-tasks,
然后你开始继续做--
and you go and you start working on--
你开始处理这个子任务 然后你明确它是什么
and you work on this sub-task, and you figure out exactly what that is.
这个子问题就分裂成三个子任务 你把它们处理完
And you find out that that breaks down into three sub-tasks, and you specify them completely,
然后你先处理这两个任务
and you go and you work on those two, and you work on this sub-one, and you specify that exactly.
解决完子任务后 你后退到这里 处理第二个子任务
And then finally when you're done, you come back way up here, and you work on your second sub-task,
然后把它详细地实现出来
and specify that out and work it out.
结束之后-- 你完成了这个美丽的大厦
And then you end up with-- you end up at the end with this beautiful edifice.
你最后得到了一棵非凡的树
Right, you end up with a marvelous tree,
你把任务划分为子任务 子任务再划分为子任务
that where you've broken your task into sub-tasks and broken each of these into sub-tasks and broken those into sub-tasks, right.
树中的每个结点都被严谨而准确地定义
And each of these nodes is exactly and precisely defined
为奇妙而精美的任务 以构建整栋大厦
to do the wonderful, beautiful task to make it fit into the whole edifice
这个就是所谓的“神话学”
Right, that's this mythology.
只有计算机科学家才可能相信你构建的复杂系统像这个样子
See only a computer scientist could possibly believe that you build a complex system like that
好了 我们用Henderson的例子来做对比
Right. Contrast that with this Henderson example.
它的结构不是那样
It didn't work like that.
事实是：这里有一个语言的层次序列
What happened was that there was a sequence of layers of language.
它是什么？
What happened?
这里有一层 允许我们构建基本图像
There was a layer of a thing that allowed us to build primitive pictures.
这个语言描述基本图像
There's primitive pictures and that was a language.
我们并没有做过多地讨论
I didn't say much about it.
我们讨论了如何构造George
We talked about how to construct George,
这个语言是在单位正方形中讨论点、线和向量
but that was a language where you talked about vectors and line segments and points and where they sat in the unit square.
而在这之上
And then on top of that, right, on top of that--
这是讨论基本图像的语言
so this is the language of primitive pictures.
讨论在特定单位正方形中线段的构造
Right, talking about line segments in particular pictures in the unit square.
在这个上面是另一个完整的语言
On top of that was a whole language.
关于几何组合子的语言
There was a language of geometric combinators,
关于几何物件的位置
a language of geometric positions,
讨论像ABOVE、BESIDE、RIGHT-PUSH和ROTATE这样的东西
which talks about things like Above and Beside and right-push and Rotate.
这些事情恰巧与我们在这个语言中谈论的事情有关
And those things, sort of, happened with reference to the things that are talked about in this language.
再细化一点 我们发现在这之上
And then if we like, we saw that above that
还有一门语言 描述组合的模式
there was sort of a language of schemes of combination.
比如说PUSH
For example, push,
也就是用一个放缩因子重复地做一件事儿
which talked about repeatedly doing something over with a scale factor.
我们在那门语言中讨论的问题
And the things that were being discussed in that language
正是我这里构建的东西
were, sort of, the things that happened down here.
我们在每一层上所讨论的对象
So what you have is, at each level, the objects that are being talked about
都是前一个层次所建立的
are the things that were erected the previous level.
这个和这个有什么区别呢？
What's the difference between this thing and this thing?
这是因为
The answer is
实际上在这里 树的每一个结点 每一次分解
that over here in the tree, each node, and in fact, each decomposition down here,
都是旨在分成确定的任务
is being designed to do a specific task,
而在另一个方案中
whereas in the other scheme,
你在每个层级上的完完全全的语言层面的能力
what you have is a full range of linguistic power at each level.
这里的每一个层次
See what's happening there, at any level,
都不是被设计为完成一个特定任务
it's not being set up to do a particular task.
它被设计为讨论整个事情
It's being set up to talk about a whole range of things.
这样设计导致的结果是：
The consequence of that for design
用这种设计方法更加健壮
is that something that's designed in that method is likely to be more robust,
我所谓的“健壮”是指
where by robust, I mean
当你在描述中做一些改变
that if you go and make some change in your description,
我们可以做出相应的改变
it's more likely to be captured by a corresponding change,
用上一层语言实现的方法改变即可
in the way that the language is implemented at the next level up,
因为你让每个层次都是完全的
right, because you've made these levels full.
所以你不需要讨论像BESIDE这样的特定操作
So you're not talking about a particular thing like Beside.
你为表达这类事物创造了完备的词汇
You've given yourself a whole vocabulary to express things of that sort,
所以当你轻微修改规格指标时
so if you go and change your specifications a little bit,
这种方法论可以捕捉并适应那些变化
it's more likely that your methodology will able to adapt to capture that change,
然而这种设计却不够健壮
whereas a design like this is not going to be robust,
因为 如果我在这里改变一下
because if I go and change something that's in here,
那可能会影响我划分这些东西的方式 严重地影响
that might affect the entire way that I decomposed everything down, further down the tree.
分解观点的最大不同在于 按层次还是严格继承分解
Right, so very big difference in outlook in decomposition, levels of language rather than, sort of, a strict hierarchy.
不只是如此 当你有多个层次的语言时
Not only that, but when you have levels of language
你就有了不同的词汇储备
you've given yourself a different vocabularies
用于讨论不同层次上的设计
for talking about the design at different levels.
我们再回过头来看看George
So if we go back and look at George one last time,
如果我想改变图像George
if I wanted to change this picture George,
我立马得到了一种不同的方式来描述变化
see suddenly I have a whole different ways of describing the change.
比如 我想在基本设计的层面上 移动某些向量的终点
Like for example, I may want to go to the basic primitive design and move the endpoint of some vector.
我会在最底层讨论这个改变
That's a change that I would discuss at the lowest level.
我会另外指定终点位置
I would say the endpoint is somewhere else.
我也可以说 我想在这个小的重复元素上做文章
Or I might come up and say, well the next thing I wanted to do, this little replicated element,
我可能想做些其它操作
I might want to do by something else.
我想在BESIDE中使用一个缩放因数
I might want to put a scale factor in that Beside.
这个改变我会在更高的层次上讨论：在组合子的层次
That's a change that I would discuss at the next level of design, the level of combinators.
我也可以改变图像的基本组合模式
Or I might want to say, I might want to change the basic way that I took this pattern
做一些递归地分解 可能不会让它们填充满角落
and made some recursive decomposition, maybe not bleeding out toward the corners or something else.
而这样的一个变化 我会在最高层次讨论
That would be a change that I would discuss at the highest level.
正是因为我按这种结构组织系统
And because I've structured the system to be this way,
我有所有的词汇 可以用不同的方式描述变化
I have all these vocabularies for talking about change in different ways
而且可以灵活地决定哪个更合适
and a lot of flexibility to decide which one's appropriate.
这就是Lisp中不同于软件工程方法论的最大要点
OK, well that's sort of a big point about the difference in software methodology that comes out from Lisp,
它来自于这样一个观点：真正的设计过程
and it all comes again, out of the notion that really, the design process
与其说是在设计程序 不如说是在设计语言
is not so much implementing programs as implementing languages.
而这就是Lisp的力量
And that's really the power of Lisp.
谢谢大家 下课
OK, thank you. Let's take a break.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/FoOTOo/Learning-SICP